Ross Brancati, MS

163 Totman Building Amherst, MA 01003 rbrancati@umass.edu 860-819-6439

PhD Student

Personal Website: rossbrancati.github.io LinkedIn: linkedin.com/in/ross-brancati/ Github: github.com/rossbrancati Twitter: twitter.com/ross brancati

Summary

PhD student with 4 years of experience in human movement science research. I use data science approaches including dimensionality reduction techniques, interpretable machine learning, and statistical models to understand the complex behavior of human movement from a systematic approach. As an avid fan of sports, I am interested in pursuing a career in data science/analytics in the field of sports science and research.

Education

2020 - Present University of Massachusetts Amherst

PhD Student in Kinesiology Concentration: Biomechanics

Graduate Certificate in Statistical and Computational Data Science

GPA: 3.93/4.0

2018 – 2019 University of Connecticut; Storrs, CT

M.S. in Biomedical Engineering Concentration: Biomechanics

GPA: 3.9/4.0

2014 – 2018 University of Connecticut; Storrs, CT

B.S. in Biomedical Engineering *Concentration: Biomechanics*

GPA: 3.5/4.0

Research Experience

Musculoskeletal & Orthopedic Biomechanics Laboratory, University of Massachusetts Amherst – Amherst, MA *Research Assistant*, August 2020 – Present

PI: Dr. Katherine Boyer

- Collect, process, and analyze large sets of biomechanics data related to musculoskeletal injuries and the aging population.
- Build interpretable machine learning models to understand the complex behavior patellofemoral pain syndrome.
- Streamline time-taxing data collection and processing procedures by developing pipelines using Python and Matlab.
- Create visualizations for presentations and publications using R/R Studio for improving data analysis and interpretation.

University of Massachusetts Men's Ice Hockey Team, University of Massachusetts Amherst – Amherst, MA

Sports Science Intern, May 2022 - Present

Supervisor: Brandon Wickett

- Leverage Catapult's wearable technology to assess movements of players during practices, games, and skill sessions.
- Support dashboard development for seamless transition of player performance data to coaches and staff.
- Analyze athlete's data to alert team staff of potential player overexertion to prevent injuries and optimize performance.

Research Experience (continued)

Orthopedic Rehabilitation and Biomechanics Laboratory, University of Michigan - Ann Arbor, MI

Research Associate 1, May 2019 – August 2020

PI: Dr. Lindsey Lepley

- Examined biomechanical implications of ACL tears in animal models using deep learning-based motion tracking system.
- Overhauled laboratory space including full synchronization of motion capture, force plate, and ultrasound systems.
- Wrote custom written scripts (Matlab) to automate data processing procedures such as muscle fiber tracking.
- Developed data processing procedures for analyzing CT scans of animal model knee joints with knee osteoarthritis.

Sports Optimization and Rehabilitation Laboratory, University of Connecticut - Storrs, CT

Graduate Researcher, December 2018 - May 2019

Co - PIs: Dr. Lindsey Lepley and Dr. Adam Lepley

- Investigated anatomical and pathological outcomes after traumatic joint injury, specifically ACL tears.
- Collected and analyzed data including kinematic, strength, muscle mechanics, neural activity, bone health, and more.
- Assisted other graduate students with ongoing projects such as tracking of muscle fibers via ultrasound recording.

Teaching and Mentorship Experience

Kinesiology Department, University of Massachusetts Amherst – Amherst, MA

Teaching Assistant, August 2020 - May 2021

Primary Lecturer: Thomas G. St. Laurent

- Teaching assistant for an undergraduate kinesiology course titled Kinesiology 100: Introduction to Kinesiology.
- Responsible for planning lessons, executing course material, and providing support for discussion section of the course.
- Topics included general kinesiology, health, nutrition, physical activity, biomechanics, and fitness testing.

Undergraduate Research Opportunity Program, University of Michigan - Ann Arbor, MI

Student Mentor, August 2019 - August 2020

Supervisor: Dr. Lindsey Lepley

- Recruit students in the Undergraduate Research Opportunities Program to participate in lab's research.
- Trained students on project specific protocols including collecting, compiling, and analyzing 3D CT scan image data.
- Simultaneously managed a total of 5 students by delegating tasks, responsibilities, and deadlines for projects.

MCB Department, University of Connecticut - Storrs, CT

Teaching Assistant, August 2018 - July 2019

- Lab teaching assistant for an undergraduate biology course titled Biology 1107: Principles of Biology 1.
- Responsible for teaching lab exercises, mentoring students, assisting students, grading, and hosting office hours.
- Learned and developed valuable skills such as lecturing, grading, and providing extra support for students.

Industry Experience

Karl Storz Endovision, Inc., Charlton, MA

Continuous Improvement Intern, May 2018 - August 2018

- Implemented lean manufacturing techniques such as Kanban and Six Sigma to improve device production.
- Improved machine shop product flow by creating an efficient work environment and improving work culture.

Medtronic PLC, North Branford, CT

Research and Design Intern, May 2017 - August 2017

- Performed feasibility and reliability testing on prototypes utilizing high tech machinery to optimize design.
- Analyzed data using Minitab to formulate statistical analysis of data sets and decide on design factors.

Publications

- White MS, Brancati RJ, Lepley LK. Joint Kinematics Dictate Subchondral Bone Remodeling in a Clinically Translational Model of Anterior Cruciate Ligament Injury. Journal of Orthopaedic Research. Accepted December 9, 2020. doi: 10.1002/jor.24943.
- 2. Davi SM, **Brancati RJ**, Lepley AS, Lepley LK. Characterizing dynamic quadriceps' morphology following anterior cruciate ligament reconstruction. The Knee. In review.

Conference Abstracts

- 1. **Brancati RJ**, Boyer KA. Data Mining Approach to Determining Gait Abnormalities in Runners with Patellofemoral Pain Syndrome. North American Congress on Biomechanics. *Oral Presentation*. Ottawa, Canada. August 21-25, 2022.
- 2. **Brancati RJ,** Kent JA, Hayes KL, Alvarado F, Boyer KA. Assessment of Aging Related Changes in Postural Control Using Time to Contact. North American Congress on Biomechanics. *Oral Presentation*. Ottawa, Canada. August 21-25, 2022.
- 3. **Brancati RJ,** Boyer KA. Biomechanical Characteristics of Runners Recently Recovered from Patellofemoral Pain Syndrome. 9th World Congress of Biomechanics. *Oral Presentation*. Taipei, Taiwan. July 10-14, 2022.
- 4. **Brancati RJ**, Kent JA, Boyer KA. Time to Contact Captures Declines in Postural Control Following Fatiguing Activity. 43rd Annual Meeting of the American Society of Biomechanics. *Oral Presentation*. Virtual Meeting. August 11, 2021.
- Brancati RJ, Boyer, KA. Time to Contact Captures Declines in Postural Control Following Fatiguing Activity. UMass Amherst School of Public Health & Health Sciences Research Day 2021. Oral Presentation. Virtual Meeting. April 16, 2021.
- 6. Davi SM, **Brancati RJ**, Lepley AS, DiStefano LJ, Lepley LK. Examining the Dynamic Complexity of the Quadriceps Following Anterior Cruciate Ligament Reconstruction. National Association of Athletic Trainers Convention. *Oral Presentation*. Orlando, Florida. June 29, 2021.
- 7. White MS, Davi SM, **Brancati RJ**, Lepley LK. Alterations in Gait and Knee Joint Alignment Substantiate New PTOA Rodent Model of ACL Injury. Orthopaedic Research Society Annual Meeting. *Oral Presentation*. Phoenix, Arizona. February 10, 2020.
- 8. Lepley LK, White MS, Davi SM, Lepley AS, **Brancati RJ**. Novel Pre-clinical Model of Post-traumatic Osteoarthritis Demonstrates Unicompartmental Declines in Trabecular Bone Volume. Orthopaedic Research Society Annual Meeting. *Poster Presentation*. Phoenix, Arizona. February 10, 2020.
- 9. Davi SM, **Brancati RJ**, Lepley LK. Characterizing Abnormalities in Dynamic Quadriceps' Function Following Anterior Cruciate Ligament Reconstruction. Orthopaedic Research Society Annual Meeting. *Poster Presentation*. Phoenix, Arizona. February 8, 2020.

Grant Applications

- 1. National Biomechanics Day Loadsol Grant (2021) Not Funded
- 2. National Biomechanics Day Loadsol Grant (2022) Not Funded
- 3. DeLuca Foundation Training Initiative (2022) Not Funded

Awards and Honors

2021	UMass Amherst School of Public Health and Health Sciences Research Day Travel Award Winner - \$1500
2020 – 2021	UMass Amherst Kinesiology Department Graduate Student Annual Travel Award - \$150
2018 – 2019	Outstanding Teaching Assistant Recognition in MCB Department
2017 – 2019	American Collegiate Hockey Association Academic All-American
2017 – 2018	University of Connecticut School of Engineering Dean's List

Memberships, Affiliations and Leadership

ı	2020 – present	American Society of Biomechanics UMass Amherst Student Chapter – Vice President
ı	2020 – present	American Society of Biomechanics Member
ı	2020 – present	National Center for Neuromodulation for Rehabilitation Member

University of Michigan Undergraduate Student Research Program Mentor

Service

2019 – 2020

2021	National Biomechanics Day 2021 Virtual Outreach Event
2022	National Biomechanics Day 2022 Outreach Event

Skills

- Python (pandas, numpy, matplotlib, statistics)
- Matlab
- R / RStudio (ggplot, tidyverse, tidyr, gt)
- Machine Learning (scikit-learn)
- Deep Learning (pytorch, tensorflow)
- Relational databases (pandas, some SQL)
- Labview
- Statistics
- CAD (Solidworks)
- Dynamic Programming

- Human Subjects Research
- Process Automation
- Finite Element Analysis (Ansys)
- Image Processing (Dragonfly ORS, 3D Slicer, CT, MRI)
- Motion Capture (Qualysis, Vicon, Visual 3D)
- Wearable Tech (IMUs)
- Electromyography (Delsys, BioPac, Neuraxon)
- Force Plates (AMTI)
- Ultrasound Imaging
- Project Management (Agile, Kanban, Six Sigma)

References

Katherine Boyer, PhD

Associate Professor

Principal Investigator, Musculoskeletal Orthopedic Biomechanics Laboratory

Department of Kinesiology

Department of Orthopedics and Physical Rehabilitation, UMass Medical School

University of Massachusetts - Amherst

Phone: (413) 545 – 1717 Email: kboyer@kin.umass.edu

Lindsey K. Lepley PhD, ATC

Associate Professor, Athletic Training

Principal Investigator, Orthopedic Rehabilitation and Biomechanics Laboratory

School of Kinesiology

University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, MI

Phone: 989-859-2950 Email: llepley@umich.edu